<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title type="text">James Black &#8211; Articles</title>
	<subtitle type="html">Epidemiologist</subtitle>
	<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
	<icon>http://epijim.co.uk/images/icon152.png</icon>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://epijim.co.uk" />
	<updated>2014-06-09T21:02:44+01:00</updated>
	<id>http://epijim.co.uk/</id>
	<author>
		<name>James Black</name>
		<uri>http://epijim.co.uk/</uri>
		<email>james.black@cantab.net</email>
	</author>
	<rights>Unless otherwise noted, all content is published under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 United States License.</rights>
	<atom10:link xmlns:atom10="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://epijim.co.uk/articles-feed.xml" />
	
	<entry>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[New Zealand and sheep]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://epijim.co.uk/articles/sheep/" />
		<id>http://epijim.co.uk/articles/sheep</id>
		<published>2014-06-08T00:00:00+01:00</published>
		<updated>2014-06-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<author>
			<name>James Black</name>
			<uri>http://epijim.co.uk</uri>
			<email>james.black@cantab.net</email>
		</author>
		<summary type="text">Does New Zealand still deserve the sheep jokes?</summary>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I say I grew up in New Zealand, a sheep joke often rears it’s head. I’ve always wondered
 how well that stereotype actually fit modern New Zealand. The claim we have 60,000,000 sheep 
 comes up fairly frequently, but I had no idea if that was close to the 
 contemporary population. Thankfully, Stats NZ provides the numbers, and below I’ve 
 plotted the numbers I got from their website.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-how-many-sheep-are-there&quot;&gt;So how many sheep are there?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So at one point there were 70,301,461 sheep in New Zealand. That was back in 1982 though.
 The number of sheep in 2013 was 30,904,714. Now I’m assuming this is sheep declared to the 
 tax man (I’m hazy on where Stats NZ got such an exact number from), but I doubt it’s too much higher 
 in reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put the numbers in context, in 2012 there were 10.8 million sheep in the UK&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and 74.4 million
 in Australia&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/images/sheep_1_sheep.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sheep_1_sheep.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;and-the-number-per-person&quot;&gt;And the number per person?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in 2013 there were 30,904,714 sheep and 4,504,600 people. So that’s 6.86 sheep to every
 person. Back in 1981 though, there 21.79 sheep to every person in New Zealand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2012 in the UK, there were 0.2 sheep per person, and 3.3 per person in Australia.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; So
 compared to the British and Australians we’re the bigger sheep lovers. After the Kiwi’s, it’s 
 the Welsh that tend to bare the brunt of the sheep jokes. In Wales there are 2.8 sheep to 
 every person - so looks like the jokes are best directed at the Kiwi’s after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/images/sheep_2_sheep.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sheep_2_sheep.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;and-how-much-is-farm-land&quot;&gt;And how much is farm land?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Zealand’s fertile lands gave it the nickname “Britain’s Breadbasket”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and, historically at least,
 huge swathes of the country were farmland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d love to know what happened in the 70’s and 80’s. 
 I’m guessing the abrupt change may have had something to do with forestry, or it could be as 
 mundane as a change in the way land was classified. The Stat NZ site doesn’t have detailed 
 breakdowns from back then but the answer must be somewhere in the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/images/sheep_3_sheep.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sheep_3_sheep.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A forestry report&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I found claims that in 2010 land use was supposedly broken down like below 
 (I’ve replotted the reports pie graph as a bar chart, although I haven’t been fully converted 
 to being a pie-chart zealot by Tufte yet&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;). While the UK was about 69% farmland and 9% forest in 2010.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite NZ having the reputation of being greener, a greater of proportion of the UK is farmland. This doesn’t seem to make sense, and there may
 be some difference in how land use is measured, but it’s also due to the fact that around 
 30% of NZ is currently a national park&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, while the proportion is only around 9% in the UK&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/images/sheep_4_sheep.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sheep_4_sheep.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was looking for the number of sheep in Australia I stumbled across
 a page on the Stats NZ site were they had already answered my first question.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; They’ve gone 
 and explored a bunch of other myths about NZ as well, and the page is well worth a gander.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;EDIT:&lt;/em&gt;: my cousin mentioned she’d like to see how the cow population has changed. Below
 I plotted the number of dairy cows, against beef cows, with deer and pigs thrown in. This data only 
 starts in the 70’s, unlike the sheep data which starts in the 30’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/images/sheep_5_cows.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sheep_5_cows.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, to put the plot above in context, with sheep as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/images/sheep_6_withsheep.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sheep_6_withsheep.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Stats NZ site http://www.stats.govt.nz/tools_and_services.aspx &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Eblex report http://www.eblex.org.uk/market-intelligence-news/uk-sheep-numbers-regional-breakdown/ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Meat and Livestock Australia http://www.mla.com.au/Cattle-sheep-and-goat-industries/Industry-overview/Sheep &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I just used wikipedia’s 2012 population estimates for the two countries. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breadbasket#New_Zealand &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ministry for Primary Industries report http://www.mpi.govt.nz/portals/0/documents/forestry/statistics/forestry-stats/facts-figures-11-12.pdf &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Edward Tufte gives the pie chart a more succinct and decisive treatment in “The Visual Display of Quantitative Information” https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2991062 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Not from the most reliable source… hccmpw.org.uk/index.php/tools/required/files/download?fID=2086 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protected_areas_of_New_Zealand &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_parks_of_England_and_Wales &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Mythbusters site http://www.stats.govt.nz/browse_for_stats/population/mythbusters.aspx &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk/articles/sheep/&quot;&gt;New Zealand and sheep&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by &lt;a href=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk/about/&quot;&gt;James Black&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk&quot;&gt;James Black&lt;/a&gt; on June 08, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[Simpson's paradox in diabetes (via javascript)]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://epijim.co.uk/articles/simpsons/" />
		<id>http://epijim.co.uk/articles/simpsons</id>
		<published>2014-04-29T00:00:00+01:00</published>
		<updated>2014-04-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<author>
			<name>James Black</name>
			<uri>http://epijim.co.uk</uri>
			<email>james.black@cantab.net</email>
		</author>
		<summary type="text">Using the D3 javascript library to visualise Simpson's paradox.</summary>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the month of July (2014) I’ll be teaching medical science for a summer school in my college.
 Over the last week I’ve started to put together the slides I’ll be using. To help explain 
 the concept of Simpson’s paradox I played around with rejigging somebody else’s code 
 to fit the context of diabetes (my research area). The code used to make 
 the plots below was originally written by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://vudlab.com/simpsons/&quot;&gt;Vudlab at UC Berkeley&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll let wikipedia give an introduction to the Simpson’s paradox,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Simpson’s paradox, or the Yule–Simpson effect, is a paradox in which a trend that appears in different groups of data disappears when these groups are combined, and the reverse trend appears for the aggregate data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Spiegelhalter, an academic who’s work I admire, contributed ideas
 to a paper on Simpson’s paradox that was published in the BMJ.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One of the examples used 
 in the paper was from the Poole diabetes cohort. The researchers broke a group of people with diabetes 
 into two groups. One required insulin (usually type 1 diabetes), the other sub-group didn’t (type 2 diabetes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They followed the two groups, and found that those with insulin dependent diabetes were 31% &lt;strong&gt;less&lt;/strong&gt;
 likely (95%CI 46% to 13%) to have died during the follow up. Yet when the adjusted for 
 age, the association flipped and those with insulin dependent diabetes were 15% &lt;strong&gt;more&lt;/strong&gt; likely 
 to have died (&lt;em&gt;statistically non-significant&lt;/em&gt;, 95%CI -9% to 46%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below, each dot represents an individual from the study. Red have 
 insulin dependent diabetes. Blue have non-insulin dependent diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;650&quot; height=&quot;260&quot; src=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk/simpsons/all.html&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next plot is just the people with insulin dependent diabetes. In this group 29% of
 people died (those that died are the red dots). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;650&quot; height=&quot;260&quot; src=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk/simpsons/insulin.html&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the next plot is the people with non-insulin dependent diabetes. In this group 40% died
 during follow up. So it looks like people are more likely to die with non-insulin dependent 
 diabetes! This really doesn’t make sense, as insulin dependent diabetes is usually assumed 
 to be a more serious manifestation of the disease (insulin is a last resort in type 2 diabetes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;650&quot; height=&quot;260&quot; src=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk/simpsons/noninsulin.html&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last plot below shows how the variable age helps explain what is happening. &lt;em&gt;Hitting the green
 button will make the individuals move between groups.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paradox occurs because people are more
 more likely to get type 2 diabetes later in life. People are also more likely to die later in 
 in life. So not accounting for the age difference in the people with the two conditions 
 means you can come to the wrong conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; src=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk/simpsons/index.html&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m planning on including these plots in my slides (the joy of HTML5 slides is being able to
 to bring in amazing plot libraries like D3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;BMJ 1994;309:1480 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk/articles/simpsons/&quot;&gt;Simpson's paradox in diabetes (via javascript)&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by &lt;a href=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk/about/&quot;&gt;James Black&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk&quot;&gt;James Black&lt;/a&gt; on April 29, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[The barons of bitcoin]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://epijim.co.uk/articles/bitcoin/" />
		<id>http://epijim.co.uk/articles/bitcoin</id>
		<published>2014-04-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
		<updated>2014-04-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<author>
			<name>James Black</name>
			<uri>http://epijim.co.uk</uri>
			<email>james.black@cantab.net</email>
		</author>
		<summary type="text">Looking closely at the hacked Mt.Gox exchange, to see if there are distinct types of traders.</summary>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Mt. Gox was a bitcoin exchange. In 2013 it was handling about 70% of all bitcoins traded globally.
 Mt. Gox is actually a truncation of &lt;em&gt;Magic: The Gathering Online Exchange&lt;/em&gt;, as Mt. Gox was 
 originally set up to help people that wear Trillby’s trade playing cards. From late 2013 users began 
 to complain that trades weren’t going through, or were delayed. By February 2014 
 Mt. Gox suspended all trading, and collapsed into bankruptcy. I’m a little hazy on what 
 actually happened, so below is wikipedia’s take:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mt. Gox announced that around 850,000 bitcoins belonging to customers and the company were missing and likely stolen, an amount valued at more than $450 million at the time. Although 200,000 bitcoins have since been “found”, the reason(s) for the disappearance—theft, fraud, mismanagement, or a combination of these—are unclear as of March 2014. There has been some speculation of internet hackers being responsible for the missing Bitcoins, but no speculation of such matter has been proven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Late 2013 hackers managed to download information on every bitcoin-to-real-money trade that
 occured between 2011 and 2013. They then released the dataset as a torrent, which is where I 
 got it from. As a word of caution, all the torrents out there seem to also have viruses, 
 so I’d avoid the dataset if you’re on windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stamen, a cartography company, did a cool post where they plotted the trades of the 500
 most prolific traders using this leaked data. They concluded that there where four types of traders, 
 and picked out four users that represented those types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/images/bitcoin_1_stamen.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bitcoin_1_stamen.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;The groups identified by Stamen.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a gander at 500 individual plots, seemed like a pretty poor way to derive these
 latent groups. As I’m going to be doing some latent class trajectory modelling in an 
 upcoming paper, and I need practice working with bigger datasets, I thought I’d have 
 have a go seeing if these groups still exist if you let the data talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s in the hacked dataset? (€ and $ trades have been changed to £ at a single, March 2014, rate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;every transaction between 1st of April 2011 and 30th November 2013, &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;which includes 8,143,064  transactions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;between 127,065 individual user accounts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;with a total of £1,554,995,828 exchanged&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to see that in rough, monthly terms,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In April 2011, the first month with data, there were
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;18,341 transactions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;between 1,112 individuals&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;with a total of £634,611 exchanged&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While in November 2013, the last month with data, there were
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;741,093 transactions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;between 34,115 individuals&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;with a total of £461,373,689 exchanged (30% of the total trades happened in the last month!)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking through the data, I should point out there was one very strange trader,
 who had a bunch of trades which were blank (no bitcoins were actually transferred) - 
 more details are in the footnotes.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So bitcoin had a pretty meteoric rise. The gif below shows the total number of trades (&lt;em&gt;x axis&lt;/em&gt;),
 against the value of the bitcoin (&lt;em&gt;y axis&lt;/em&gt;), for each month I have data on. You can see the 
 number of trades each month rises till late 2011, which corresponds with the first time a hacker 
 managed to steal bitcoins from Mt. Gox. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/images/bitcoin_2b_gif.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bitcoin_2b_gif.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Increasing number of trades and value of a bitcoin over time.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next plot shows the huge increase in value of a bitcoin over time. From April till June, in
 2011, the price went from less than a pound, to over £100. After this first bubble burst, 
 it wasn’t till 2013 till the price recovered - before it promptly went all the way up to 
 more than £1000 pounds. So a £1 investment in 2011 would net you 
 a £1000 pounds per coin gain in 2013 - hindsight is 
 just a bit cruel sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/images/bitcoin_2_value.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bitcoin_2_value.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Increasing value of the bitcoin over time.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as time went by, and the value of a bitcoin rose, did the amount of money changing hands
 in each trade also go up? The following gif plots the median value of each trade against, against 
 the median value of a bitcoin, at month intervals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/images/bitcoin_2a_gif.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bitcoin_2a_gif.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Increasing number of trades and value of a bitcoin over time.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So getting back to the Stamen’s idea of their being four types of traders amongst the top 500
 on Mt. Gox. Looking at 500 separate plots and subjectively making four groups is a little 
 dubious. Group Based Trajectory Models take the subjective out of grouping trajectories, 
 and let the data itself drive the groupings. So I decided to use such a model to see if there 
 are prominent groups of traders amongst the 127,065 traders I had data on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Now this all needs to be taken with a grain of salt. This model is full of outliers, and I’m
 using pretty contrived proxies as the dependent and independent variables. I didn’t follow the usual process
 of using BIC and AIC to decide on the number of groups. Instead, I just modelled 4-8 groups, 
 and took the ones that looked interesting (The BIC suggests I should of made more than six groups). 
 Even with the 16GB of RAM on my laptop, each model took around 2 hours to converge, which is 
 why I didn’t spend time fine tuning the model.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So the following results are not intended to be a robust analysis - I’m doing this to get 
to learn the R packages. I happen to be using the bitcoin dataset just because it’s interesting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in the next plot, I’m looking at total monthly balance of their account. I.e, if they brought
 £10 of coins, and sold £12, that net £2 is what I’m interested in. I did it this way as I want to 
 see who was holding on to their coins over time. Going in I thought there would be three groups,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Miners, accounts that mainly sell mined bitcoins&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dabblers, people that don’t really trade, or just buy coins for specific purchases, and keep their monthly balance around zero.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gamblers, people that have brought up coins and sat on them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model though identified that there were at least six latent trajectories in the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;http://cdn.oesmith.co.uk/morris-0.4.2.min.css&quot; /&gt;
    
    &lt;script src=&quot;http://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.9.0/jquery.min.js&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src=&quot;http://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/raphael/2.1.0/raphael-min.js&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src=&quot;http://cdn.oesmith.co.uk/morris-0.4.2.min.js&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    
    &lt;style&gt;
    .rChart {
      display: block;
      margin-left: auto; 
      margin-right: auto;
      width: 600px;
      height: 400px;
    }  
    &lt;/style&gt;
    
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;div id=&quot;chart4cb6355754b3&quot; class=&quot;rChart morris&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  
    
    &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    var chartParams = {
 &quot;element&quot;: &quot;chart4cb6355754b3&quot;,
&quot;width&quot;:            600,
&quot;height&quot;:            400,
&quot;xkey&quot;: &quot;Date&quot;,
&quot;ykeys&quot;: [
 &quot;Traj_1&quot;,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;,
&quot;Traj_6&quot; 
],
&quot;data&quot;: [
 {
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2011-04-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 36,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 2,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: 8,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 7,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: -1,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 1,
&quot;X&quot;: 1 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2011-05-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 15,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 2,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: 3,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 7,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: 2,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 1,
&quot;X&quot;: 2 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2011-06-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 8,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 3,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: 1,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 6,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: 4,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 2,
&quot;X&quot;: 3 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2011-07-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 5,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 3,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -2,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 6,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: 7,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 2,
&quot;X&quot;: 4 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2011-08-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 3,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 4,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -3,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 6,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: 10,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 2,
&quot;X&quot;: 5 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2011-09-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 2,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 4,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -5,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 6,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: 12,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 2,
&quot;X&quot;: 6 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2011-10-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 2,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 4,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -7,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 6,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: 12,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 3,
&quot;X&quot;: 7 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2011-11-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 2,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 5,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -9,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 6,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: 12,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 3,
&quot;X&quot;: 8 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2011-12-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 2,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 5,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -11,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 6,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: 10,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 2,
&quot;X&quot;: 9 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2012-01-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 2,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 5,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -13,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 6,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: 7,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 2,
&quot;X&quot;: 10 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2012-02-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 2,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 5,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -14,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 6,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: 5,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 2,
&quot;X&quot;: 11 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2012-03-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 3,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 5,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -13,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 7,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: 3,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 2,
&quot;X&quot;: 12 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2012-04-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 4,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 5,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -12,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 7,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: 2,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 2,
&quot;X&quot;: 13 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2012-05-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 5,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 4,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -11,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 8,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: 1,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 2,
&quot;X&quot;: 14 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2012-06-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 6,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 4,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -9,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 9,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: -1,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 2,
&quot;X&quot;: 15 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2012-07-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 8,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 4,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -8,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 9,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: -2,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 2,
&quot;X&quot;: 16 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2012-08-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 11,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 3,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -6,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 10,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: -4,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 1,
&quot;X&quot;: 17 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2012-09-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 14,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 3,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -5,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 11,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: -6,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 1,
&quot;X&quot;: 18 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2012-10-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 18,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 2,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -4,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 13,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: -9,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 1,
&quot;X&quot;: 19 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2012-11-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 22,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 2,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -3,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 14,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: -13,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 1,
&quot;X&quot;: 20 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2012-12-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 25,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 2,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -2,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 16,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: -18,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 1,
&quot;X&quot;: 21 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2013-01-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 27,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: 1,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -2,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 18,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: -21,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 1,
&quot;X&quot;: 22 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2013-02-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 26,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: -1,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -2,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 20,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: -22,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 1,
&quot;X&quot;: 23 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2013-03-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 24,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: -1,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -1,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 23,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: -21,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 1,
&quot;X&quot;: 24 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2013-04-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 19,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: -2,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -1,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 26,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: -17,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 2,
&quot;X&quot;: 25 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2013-05-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 14,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: -3,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -1,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 29,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: -12,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 2,
&quot;X&quot;: 26 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2013-06-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 9,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: -4,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -1,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 32,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: -7,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 2,
&quot;X&quot;: 27 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2013-07-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 5,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: -5,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -1,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 37,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: -3,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 3,
&quot;X&quot;: 28 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2013-08-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: 2,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: -7,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -1,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 41,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: -1,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 4,
&quot;X&quot;: 29 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2013-09-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: -1,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: -11,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -1,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 46,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: 3,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 6,
&quot;X&quot;: 30 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2013-10-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: -3,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: -16,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -2,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 51,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: 12,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 10,
&quot;X&quot;: 31 
},
{
 &quot;Date&quot;: &quot;2013-11-01&quot;,
&quot;Traj_1&quot;: -11,
&quot;Traj_2&quot;: -25,
&quot;Traj_3&quot;: -2,
&quot;Traj_4&quot;: 57,
&quot;Traj_5&quot;: 66,
&quot;Traj_6&quot;: 16,
&quot;X&quot;: 32 
} 
],
yLabelFormat: function (y) { return y.toString() + &#39; pounds&#39;; },
&quot;pointSize&quot;:              0,
&quot;lineWidth&quot;:              1,
&quot;id&quot;: &quot;chart4cb6355754b3&quot;,
&quot;labels&quot;: [ &quot;Traj_1 (18%)&quot;, &quot;Traj_2 (5%)&quot;, &quot;Traj_3 (1%)&quot;, &quot;Traj_4 (52%)&quot;, &quot;Traj_5 (3%)&quot;, &quot;Traj_6 (20%)&quot; ] 
},
      chartType = &quot;Line&quot;
    new Morris[chartType](chartParams)
&lt;/script&gt;
    
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how many people are in each group? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;18% in Traj_1, 
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;hoarders, who brought in early and again as the price rose in early 2013&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5% in Traj_2, 
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;silk roaders? This is the group that hung around a monthly balance of zero. They either don’t trade much, or were balancing out their trades, presumably buying and spending bitcoins evenly. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1% in Traj_3, 
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;miners, brought in a little at the start, but then consistently only sold bitcoins&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;52% in Traj_4, 
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;chumps, brought in heavily, particularly right up to the exchange collapsing&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3% in Traj_5, 
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the traders, brought when the price was low (2012) sold when it was high (2013). A proportion invested massively in bitcoin just before the dataset ends, which skews this group in the last month.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;20% in Traj_6, 
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;like the silk roaders, but they had began to amass some coins before the exchange closed&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which means, there is still more than 1700 people represented by trajectory 3, the smallest group representing 1%!
 In the plot above, the top 500 of the Stamen post 
 will be completely drowned out by the 100,000+ traders that, as you can see, tend to trade 
 relatively small amounts. &lt;em&gt;I should stress, this six group model does not fit well&lt;/em&gt;. Each individual is 
 assigned a probability of being within each of the six trajectories. A mean probability of &amp;gt;0.7 for 
 each group is considered the absolute minimum for a model that explains the data well. This 
 model averages around 0.65. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-what-happens-if-i-look-just-within-the-top-500-like-stamen-did-in-their-post&quot;&gt;So what happens if I look just within the top 500, like Stamen did in their post?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Stamen, I also subsetted the data so it was just the 500 people that traded the most by volume.
 As the underlying distributions in the whole sample weren’t ideal, for the top 500 I’ve used a 
 mediod based clustering approach. So rather than finding trajectories that are similar and grouping 
 them, this time I can’t taken the following three characteristics, and grouped people based 
 on who is similar to who,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;total &lt;em&gt;balance&lt;/em&gt;, which gives an indication if they stockpiled bitcoins, sold (maybe mined?) bitcoins, or brought as much as they sold&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;total number of trades over the years I have data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the median price they paid for a bitcoin, to try and get an indication on wether they brought in when it was cheap, or didn’t start till it was expensive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data suggested there are six groups. Below are violin plots showing the distribution
 of the three characteristics used to make the groups, by the groups that were derived. The 
 numbers in each grouped were as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;G1, 69 people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;G2, 392 people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;G3, 121 people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;G4, 7 people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;G5, 185 people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;G6, 201 people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;G7, 420 people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;G8, 415 people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;G9, 459 people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the these plots, possible the group “G9” were the unfortunate souls that Stamen
 suggests brought into bitcoin late. Although, as I’ve seen the model fit, I would probably 
 conclude that the methods we use to cluster people and trajectories in medical research 
 don’t cope very well with the chaotic distributions present in financial data, and these 
 models don’t really tell us much. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like in this case, Stamen eyeballing some graphs 
 and coming up with groups is probably outperforming both my group based trajectory model, and 
 my mediod based take on k-means clustering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/images/bitcoin_3_kmeansgroups.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bitcoin_3_kmeansgroups.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Violin plots characterising the groups.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It’s important to note that this those not mean £1.5 billion pounds was ever in the exchange. For example, a silk road user may buy bitcoin to buy something, then a day later the seller may recirculate the same bitcoins to get the payment out as cash. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;One trader stands out as rather strange. &lt;em&gt;TIBANNE_LIMITED_HK&lt;/em&gt;, a pretty prolific trader. In 272,007 trades they traded with themselves, although zero coins actually changed hands. I don’t fully understand what’s going on, but I think they are big brokerage for bitcoins, and so these might be automated transfers. I recommend googling &lt;em&gt;“Mt.Gox TIBANNE_LIMITED_HK”&lt;/em&gt; if you’re interested. A surprising number of individuals link this trader to numerous new world order conspiracies, which is also why I didn’t find a site I felt comfortable linking to myself. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk/articles/bitcoin/&quot;&gt;The barons of bitcoin&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by &lt;a href=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk/about/&quot;&gt;James Black&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk&quot;&gt;James Black&lt;/a&gt; on April 18, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[GradCon 2014 poster]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://epijim.co.uk/articles/GradCon2014/" />
		<id>http://epijim.co.uk/articles/GradCon2014</id>
		<published>2014-04-15T00:00:00+01:00</published>
		<updated>2014-04-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<author>
			<name>James Black</name>
			<uri>http://epijim.co.uk</uri>
			<email>james.black@cantab.net</email>
		</author>
		<summary type="text">My poster from the Jesus College Graduate Conference 2014.</summary>
		<content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/images/gradcon2014_poster.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/gradcon2014_poster.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;My poster from the Jesus College Graduate Conference 2014.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above is a copy of my poster from the 2014 Jesus College Graduate conference. It’s the first
 poster I’ve made in R. It also won the best poster award, so it’s also the first poster that
 was both fun to make, and financially rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;


		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk/articles/GradCon2014/&quot;&gt;GradCon 2014 poster&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by &lt;a href=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk/about/&quot;&gt;James Black&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk&quot;&gt;James Black&lt;/a&gt; on April 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[Publish or perish - there's a model for that.]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://epijim.co.uk/articles/hindex/" />
		<id>http://epijim.co.uk/articles/hindex</id>
		<published>2014-04-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
		<updated>2014-04-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<author>
			<name>James Black</name>
			<uri>http://epijim.co.uk</uri>
			<email>james.black@cantab.net</email>
		</author>
		<summary type="text">Scraping Google Scholar for publications and predicting an h index.</summary>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A rather contentious talking point in academia is the belief that it’s publish or perish.
 Fanning the flames of this debate are measures like the H-index&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which attempt to distill 
 a researchers impact on the body of knowledge into a single metric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Top explain the H-index, I’ll rely on the quote below, which was written by Daniel Acuna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One popular measure of success is physicist Jorge Hirsch’s h-index, which captures the quality (citations) and quantity (number) of papers, thus representing scientific achievements better than either factor alone. A scientist has an h-index of n if he or she has published n articles receiving at least n citations each. Einstein, Darwin and Feynman, for example, have impressive h-indices of 96, 63 and 53, respectively. According to Hirsch, an h-index of 12 for a physicist — meaning 12 papers with at least 12 citations each — could qualify him or her for tenure at a major university.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acuna and his co-authors developed a model to predict future H-index&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, based on
 previous publications and citations. Their sample contained 3,085 neuroscientists, 
 57 Drosophila researchers and 151 evolutionary scientists. From this population they built, 
 and published, a model that explains about the same amount of variation in the outcome as 
 the cardiovascular disease (CVD) risk score that is recommended for use in UK practices. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike a CVD risk score though, there has been no external validations, so we don’t know how
 well this model performs outside of the 3,000ish neuroscientists…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with a plethora of caveats in hand - like always - there is an R package to connect this
 model to people’s Google Scholar profiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I should stress now that I consider this model, and the H-index in general, a fun metric to play with. And not a true measure of the relevance and impact of someones research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So first the packages needed to run this analysis. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;r&quot;&gt;library&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;devtools&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# get the latest version&lt;/span&gt;
install_github&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;jkeirstead/scholar&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# google scholar package&lt;/span&gt;
library&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;xkcd&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# xkcd graphs!&lt;/span&gt;
library&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;extrafont&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# xkcd fonts&lt;/span&gt;
library&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;ggplot2&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# best package ever&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And check the connection with google scholar. For the &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt;, it’s the bit after &lt;em&gt;user=&lt;/em&gt; in
 your google scholar profile url.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;r&quot;&gt;id_j &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;-S7V41QAAAAJ&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
james &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; get_profile&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;id_j&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
attach&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;james&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  name &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# me!&lt;/span&gt;
  total_cites &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# 1129 (although only as I&amp;#39;m one of 300 people&lt;/span&gt;
              &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# on the WHO Global Burden of Disease paper&lt;/span&gt;
  h_index &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# 5&lt;/span&gt;
  i10_index &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# 3&lt;/span&gt;
detach&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;james&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now I’ll scrape one of my two supervisors pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;r&quot;&gt;id_s &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;6WC1bewAAAAJ&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
simon &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; get_profile&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;id_s&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
attach&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;simon&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  name &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# Simon Griffin MBBS MSc DM FRCGP&lt;/span&gt;
  total_cites &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# 9673&lt;/span&gt;
  h_index &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# 50&lt;/span&gt;
  i10_index &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# 118&lt;/span&gt;
detach&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;simon&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The google scholar package allows you to compare the citations for different authors over time.
 In the following code block I pull the citations per year for myself, one of my supervisors, 
 and the Winston Professor for the Public Understanding of Risk (an academic at Cambridge with 
 one of my dream jobs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;r&quot;&gt;ids &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; c&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;oz7MFu0AAAAJ&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; id_s&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;id_j&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# Compare their career trajectories, based on year of first citation&lt;/span&gt;
df &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; compare_scholar_careers&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;ids&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

xrange &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; range&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;df&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;career_year&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
yrange &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; range&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;df&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;cites&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

png&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;hindex_plot1.png&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;width&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;800&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
ggplot&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;df&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; aes&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;x&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;career_year&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; y&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;cites&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
  geom_line&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;aes&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;linetype&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;name&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;colour&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;name&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
  xkcdaxis&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;xrange&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;yrange&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
  ylab&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Citations that year&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
  xlab&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Year since first citation&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
  ggtitle&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;expression&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;atop&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Comparing citations&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
                          atop&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;italic&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Cam&amp;#39;s Prof of Risk, my supervisor and me&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
  theme&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;legend.position&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;c&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0.3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0.85&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
dev.off&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/images/hindex_plot1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hindex_plot1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Citations by year.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my career is quite a bit behind - but as I’m only in the 2nd year of my PhD, I’m also
 not really an academic yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to the H-index. The following code will use the google scholar profiles of myself and
 the two other people who’s data I pulled to calculate the predicted trajectories of our H-indexes over 
 the next 10-years. As I mentioned before - this model has not been validated in epidemiologists, 
 so this is just for interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;## Predict my h-index&lt;/span&gt;
simon_h &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; predict_h_index&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;id_s&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; 
  simon_h&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;name &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Prof Griffin&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
james_h &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; predict_h_index&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;id_j&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  james_h&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;name &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;James Black&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
david_h &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; predict_h_index&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;oz7MFu0AAAAJ&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  david_h&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;name &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Prof Spiegelhalter&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;

h_index &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; rbind&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;simon_h&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;james_h&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
h_index &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; rbind&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;h_index&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;david_h&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I have a dataframe with predicted H-indexes, so I can plot them. Using an XKCD theme
 of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;r&quot;&gt;xrange &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; range&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;h_index&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;years_ahead&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
yrange &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; range&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;h_index&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;h_index&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

png&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;hindex_plot2.png&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;width&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;800&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
ggplot&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;h_index&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; aes&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;x&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;years_ahead&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; y&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;h_index&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
  geom_line&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;aes&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;linetype&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;name&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;colour&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;name&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
  xkcdaxis&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;xrange&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;yrange&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
  ylab&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Predicted H index&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
  xlab&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Years from 2014&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
  ggtitle&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;expression&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;atop&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Predicting H index over the next 10 years&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
                          atop&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;italic&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;For Cam&amp;#39;s Prof of Risk, my supervisor and me&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
  theme&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;legend.position&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;c&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0.60&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0.40&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
dev.off&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/images/hindex_plot2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hindex_plot2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Predicted H-index from April 2014 onwards.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So according to this model my H-index should increase from it’s current level of 5, to 16 in 10-years time. 10-years
 from now it will be 8.5 years since I submitted my PhD. So I would be incredibly stoked 
 to have 16 papers with more than 16 citations for each. Better yet, it suggests my 
 current trajectory seems to avoid &lt;em&gt;perish&lt;/em&gt;. Sadly, I don’t have much faith in the prophetic 
 abilities of this model, especially as it’s based off only a handful of publications. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also really hoping no-one at a funding
 body or fellowship board gets carried away with this model. I’m afraid that the big winners from 
 these sorts of scores becoming more important would be 
 the vanity publishers like Hindawi and Dove Press, who will publish anything for a fee. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hirsch. &lt;em&gt;Proc. Natl Acad. Sci.&lt;/em&gt; USA 102, 16569–16572 (&lt;strong&gt;2005&lt;/strong&gt;) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Acuna. &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; 489, 201–202 (&lt;strong&gt;2012&lt;/strong&gt;) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk/articles/hindex/&quot;&gt;Publish or perish - there's a model for that.&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by &lt;a href=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk/about/&quot;&gt;James Black&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;http://epijim.co.uk&quot;&gt;James Black&lt;/a&gt; on April 11, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
	</entry>
	
</feed>